{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "5.1","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["1.5 g", "4.0 g", "7.5 g", "15.0 g"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "7.5 g","explanation": "A percent solution expressed in w/v refers to grams of solute per 100.0 mL of solution. To calculate, multiply the percentage (as grams) by the volume needed (mL), and then divide by 100.0 (mL). (5.0 g × 150.0 mL) ÷ 100.0 mL = 7.5 g To prepare the solution, weigh 7.5 g of NaOH pellets, and add to a 150.0-mL volumetric flask. Add sufficient deionized H2O to dissolve the NaOH. After the solution cools, add deionized H2O to the 150.0 mL line on the flask, and mix again"},"question": "How many grams of sodium hydroxide (NaOH) are required to prepare 150.0 mL of a 5.0% weight/volume (w/v) solution?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Solutions/2"},{"choices": ["10.0 mL", "20.0 mL", "100.0 mL", "200.0 mL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "200.0 mL","explanation": "The expression percent v/v refers to the volume of one liquid in milliliters present in 100.0 mL of solution. To calculate, multiply the percentage (as mL) by the volume required (mL), then divide by 100 (mL). (10.0 mL × 2000.0 mL) ÷ 100.0 mL = 200.0 mL To prepare 2.0 L of a 10.0% v/v solution of acetic acid, add approximately 1.0 L of deionized H2O to a 2.0 L volumetric flask. Add 200.0 mL of glacial acetic acid, and mix. Then, add sufficient deionized H2O to bring the meniscus to the 2.0 L line, and mix again"},"question": "How many milliliters of glacial acetic acid are needed to prepare 2.0 L of 10.0% v/v acetic acid?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Solutions/2"},{"choices": ["5.4 g", "6.1 g", "15.0 g", "17.0 g"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "15.0 g","explanation": "Determine the mass of CuSO4 • 5H2O containing 9.6 g of anhydrous CuSO4. First, calculate the percentage of CuSO4 in the hydrate, and then divide the amount needed (9.6 g) by the percentage. % CuSO4 = molecular weight (MW) CuSO4 ÷ MW CuSO4 • 5H2O × 100 = (159.7 ÷ 249.7) × 100 = 63.96% Grams CuSO4 • 5H2O = 9.6 g ÷ 0.6396 = 15.0 g A convenient formula to use is: g hydrate = (MW hydrate ÷ MW anhydrous salt) × g anhydrous sal"},"question": "A biuret reagent requires preparation of a stock solution containing 9.6 g of copper II sulfate (CuSO4) per liter. How many grams of QuSO4 • 5H2O are needed to prepare 1.0 L of the stock solution? Atomic weights: H = 1.0; Cu = 63.6; O = 16.0; S = 32.1","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Reagent preparation/2"},{"choices": ["89.5 mL", "126.0 mL", "130.5 mL", "180.0 mL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "130.5 mL","explanation": "The MW of HNO3 is 63.0 g. Because the valance of the acid is 1 (1 mole of hydrogen is produced per mole of acid), the equivalent weight is also 63.0 g. The mass needed is calculated by multiplying the normality (2.0 N) by the equivalent weight (63.0 g) and volume (1.0 L); therefore, 126.0 g of acid are required. Because the purity is 68.0% and the specific gravity 1.42, the amount of HNO3 in grams per milliliter is 0.68 × 1.42 g/mL or 0.9656 g/mL. The volume required is calculated by dividing the mass needed (126.0 g) by the grams per milliliter. mL HNO3 = 126.0 g ÷ 0.9656 g/mL = 126.0 g × 1.0 mL/0.9656 g = 130.5 m"},"question": "How many milliliters of nitric acid (HNO3) (purity 68.0%, specific gravity 1.42) are needed to prepare 1.0 L of a 2.0 N solution? Atomic weights: H = 1.0; N = 14.0; O = 16.0","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Reagent preparation/2"},{"choices": ["0.25", "0.40", "2.5", "0.4"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "2.5","explanation": "The SI unit is the recommended method of reporting clinical laboratory results. The SI unit for all electrolytes is millimoles per liter (mmol/L). To convert from milligrams per deciliter to mmol/L, multiply by 10 to convert to milligrams per liter, then divide by the atomic mass expressed in milligrams. 10.0 mg/dL × 10.0 dL/1.0 L = 100.0 mg/L 100.0 mg/L × 1.0 mmol/40.1 mg = 2.5 mmol/"},"question": "Convert 10.0 milligrams per deciliter (mg/dL) calcium (atomic weight = 40.1) to the International System of Units (SI).","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/SI unit conversion/2"},{"choices": ["0.8 mg/dL", "1.2 mg/dL", "2.4 mg/dL", "4.9 mg/dL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "2.4 mg/dL","explanation": "To convert from mEq/L to mg/dL, first calculate the milliequivalent weight (equivalent weight expressed in milligrams), which is the atomic mass divided by the valence. Because magnesium is divalent, each mole has the charge equivalent of 2 moles of hydrogen. Then, multiply the mEq/L by the milliequivalent weight to convert to milligrams per liter (mg/L). Next, divide by 10 to convert mg/L to mg/dL. Milliequivalent weight Mg = 24.3 ÷ 2 = 12.15 mg/mEq 2.0 mEq/L × 12.15 mg/mEq = 24.3 mg/L 24.3 mg/L × 1.0 L/10.0 dL = 2.4 mg/d"},"question": "Convert 2.0 milliequivalents per liter (mEq/L) magnesium (atomic weight = 24.3) to mg/dL.","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Unit conversion/2"},{"choices": ["1.5 mL", "7.5 mL", "15.0 mL", "25.0 mL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "7.5 mL","explanation": "To calculate the volume of stock solution needed, divide the concentration of working standard by the concentration of stock standard, and then multiply by the volume of working standard that is needed. C1 × V1 = C2 × V2, where C1 = concentration of stock standard V1 = volume of stock standard C2 = concentration of working standard V2 = volume of working standard 2000.0 mg/dL × V1 = 150.0 mg/dL × 100.0 mL V1 = (150.0 ÷ 2000.0) × 100.0 mL V1 = 7.5 m"},"question": "How many milliliters of a 2000.0 mg/dL glucose stock solution are needed to prepare 100.0 mL of a 150.0 mg/dL glucose working standard?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Solutions/2"},{"choices": ["1.0", "1.6", "2.5", "2.8"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "1.6","explanation": "For a strong acid, the pH is equal to the negative logarithm of the H+ concentration. pH = –Log H+ pH = –Log 0.025 pH = 1."},"question": "What is the pH of a solution of HNO3, if the hydrogen ion (H+) concentration is 2.5 × 10–2 M?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/pH/2"},{"choices": ["4.2", "7.2", "9.2", "11.2"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "9.2","explanation": "First, calculate the pOH of the solution. pOH = –Log [OH–] pOH = –Log 1.5 × 10–5 = 4.82 pH = 14 – pOH pH = 14 – 4.8 = 9."},"question": "Calculate the pH of a solution of 1.5 × 10–5 molar (M) ammonium hydroxide (NH4OH).","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/pH/2"},{"choices": ["1", "2", "3", "4"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "2","explanation": "When zeros appear by themselves to the left of the decimal point, they are not significant. When they are to the left of the decimal point and are preceded or followed by a number, they are significant. Zeros after the decimal point preceding a number are not significant. However, they are significant if they follow another number (either before or after the decimal point) or are between two numbers. Therefore, 0.060 M has only two significant figures (the underlined digits). In laboratory practice, most analytes are reported with two significant figures. Routine analytes that are exceptions are pH, which includes three significant figures, and analytes with whole numbers above 100, such as sodium, cholesterol, triglycerides, and glucose"},"question": "How many significant figures should be reported when the pH of a 0.060 M solution of HNO3 is calculated?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Significant figures/2"},{"choices": ["1.7", "3.0", "4.3", "4.6"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "3.0","explanation": "Weak acids are not completely ionized, and pH must be calculated from the dissociation constant of the acid (in this case 1.75 × 10–5)"},"question": "What is the pH of a 0.05 M solution of acetic acid? Dissociation constant (Ka) = 1.75 × 10–5, pKa = 4.76","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/pH/2"},{"choices": ["1.35", "2.25", "5.75", "6.12"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "2.25","explanation": "The Henderson-Hasselbalch equation can be used to determine the pH of a buffer containing a weak acid and a salt of the acid"},"question": "What is the pH of a buffer containing 40.0 mmol/L NaHC2O4 and 4.0 mmol/L H2C2O4? pKa = 1.25","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/pH/2"},{"choices": ["1.96 g", "2.61 g", "2.72 g", "19.2 g"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "2.61 g","explanation": "The Henderson-Hasselbalch equation is used to calculate the ratio of salt to acid needed to give a pH of 3.50. Rearranging gives KH2PO4 = 23.99 × H3PO4. Because the phosphate in the buffer is 20.0 mmol/L, then H3PO4 + KH2PO4 must equal 20. Because KH2PO4 = 23.99 × H3PO4, then: To determine the grams required, multiply the moles of KH2PO4 by the formula weight. 0.0192 mol/L × 136.1 g/mol = 2.613 "},"question": "A solvent needed for high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) requires a 20.0 mmol/L phosphoric acid buffer, pH 3.50, made by mixing potassium dihydrogen phosphate (KH2PO4) and phosphoric acid (H3PO4). How many grams of KH2PO4 are required to make 1.0 L of this buffer? Formula weights: KH2PO4 = 136.1; H3PO4 = 98.0; pKa H3PO4 = 2.12","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Buffers/2"},{"choices": ["123 mg/dL", "172 mg/dL", "232 mg/dL", "314 mg/dL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "172 mg/dL","explanation": "Cu = Au/As × Cs where Cu = concentration of unknown, Au= absorbance of unknown, As = absorbance of standard, and Cs = concentration of standard. Cu = 0.740/0.860 × 200 mg/Dl = 172 mg/d"},"question": "A procedure for cholesterol is calibrated with a serum-based cholesterol standard that was determined by the Abell-Kendall method to be 200.0 mg/dL. Assuming the same volume of sample and reagent are used, calculate the cholesterol concentration in the patient’s sample from the following results: Standard Concentration Absorbance of Reagent Blank Absorbance of Standard Absorbance of Patient Serum 200 mg/dL 0.00 0.860 0.740","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Beer’s law/2"},{"choices": ["119 mg/dL", "131 mg/dL", "156 mg/dL", "180 mg/dL"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "131 mg/dL","explanation": "The serum blank absorbance is subtracted from the result for the patient’s serum before applying the ratiometric formula to calculate concentration. Cu = [(Au – ASB)/As] × Cs where ASB = absorbance of serum blank = (0.750–0.100)/0.620 × 125 mg/dL = 131 mg/d"},"question": "A glycerol kinase method for triglyceride calls for a serum blank in which lipase is absent from the reagent in order to measure endogenous glycerol. Given the following results, and assuming the same volume of sample and reagent are used for each test, calculate the triglyceride concentration in the patient’s sample.","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Beer’s law/2"},{"choices": ["26 IU/L", "326 IU/L", "1228 IU/L", "1290 IU/L"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "1290 IU/L","explanation": "An international unit (IU) is defined as 1 μmol (micromole) of substrate consumed or product produced per minute. The micromoles of NADH consumed in this reaction are determined by dividing the change in absorbance per minute by the absorbance of 1 μmol of NADH. Because 1 mol/L/cm would have an absorbance of 6.22 × 103 absorbance units, then 1 μmol/mL/cm would produce an absorbance of 6.22. Therefore, dividing the ΔΑ per minute by 6.22 gives the micromoles of NADH consumed in the reaction. This is multiplied by the dilution of serum to determine the micromoles per minute per milliliter, and multiplied by 1,000 to convert to liters. where TV is total volume and SV is sample volum"},"question": "A procedure for aspartate aminotransferase (AST) is performed manually because of a repeating error code for nonlinearity obtained on the laboratory’s automated chemistry analyzer; 0.05 mL of serum and 1.0 mL of substrate are used. The reaction rate is measured at 30°C at 340 nm using a 1.0 cM light path, and the delta absorbance (–ΔΑ) per minute is determined to be 0.382. Based on a molar absorptivity coefficient for nicotinamide adenine dinucleotide (NADH) at 340 nm of 6.22 × 103 M–1 cM–1 L–1, calculate the enzyme activity in international units (IUs) per liter.","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/International units/2"},{"choices": ["The 95% confidence interval for the mean","The range that includes 50% of the results","The central 68% of results","The range encompassed by ±2.5 standard deviations(s)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The 95% confidence interval for the mean","explanation": "The acceptable range for QC results is often set at the 95% confidence interval. This is defined as the range between –1.96s and +1.96s. This means that we can expect a QC result to fall within this range 95 out of 100 times. For practical purposes, this is the same as ±2s (95.4 out of 100 results should fall within ±2s of the mean on the basis of chance). However, this limit will result in a high rate of false rejections (rejecting good results) when the assay has a low bias and coefficient of variation (CV) (in other words, performs significantly better that the allowable error limit for the test)"},"question": "When referring to conventional quality control (QC) results, what parameter usually determines the acceptable range?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to assess validity/Accuracy of procedures/Quality control/1"},{"choices": ["12s", "22s", "13s", "14s"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "12s","explanation": "The notation 12S means that one control is outside ±2 standard deviation units. QC results follow the bell-shaped curve called the Gaussian (normal) distribution. If a control is assayed 100 times, 68 out of 100 results would fall within +1s and –1s of the mean. Ninety-five (95.4) out of 100 results would fall within +2s and –2s. This leaves only 5 out of 100 results (1:20) that fall outside the ±2s limit. Also, 99.7 out of 100 results fall within ±3s of the mean"},"question": "Which of the following QC rules would be broken one out of 20 times by chance alone?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to assess validity/Accuracy of procedures/Quality control/1"},{"choices": ["Two consecutive controls greater than 2s above or below the mean","Three consecutive controls greater than 1s above the mean","Four controls steadily increasing in value but less than ±1s from the mean","One control above +1s and the other below –1s from the mean"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Two consecutive controls greater than 2s above or below the mean","explanation": "Rejecting a run when three consecutive controls fall between 1 and 2s or when a trend of four increasing or decreasing control results occurs would lead to frequent rejection of valid analytical runs. Appropriate control limits are four consecutive controls above or below 1s (41s) to detect a significant shift, and a cumulative sum control chart (CUSUM) result exceeding the ±2.7s limit to detect a significant shift or trend. When controls deviate in opposite directions, the difference should exceed 4s before the run is rejected"},"question": "Using conventional QC rules, which of the following conditions is cause for rejecting an analytical run?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Select course of action/Quality control/3"},{"choices": ["Poor precision has led to random error (RE)","A systematic error (SE) is present","Proportional error is present","QC material is contaminated"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Poor precision has led to random error (RE)","explanation": "When control results deviate from the mean in opposite direction, the run is affected by RE, which results from imprecision. An analytical run is rejected when two controls within the same run have an algebraic difference in excess of 4s (R4s). The R4S rule is applied only to controls within a run (level 1 – level 2), never across runs or days"},"question": "One of two controls within a run is above +2s and the other control is below –2s from the mean. What do these results indicate?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize problems/Quality control/2"},{"choices": ["1:100", "5:100", "1:400", "1:1,600"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "1:1,600","explanation": "QC results follow a Gaussian or normal distribution. Ninety-five percent of the results fall within ±2s of the mean; therefore, 2.5 out of 100 (1:40) are above +2s and 2.5 out of 100 are below –2s. The probability of two consecutive controls being beyond –2s is the product of their individual probabilities. 1/40 × 1/40 = 1/1,600 trials by chance"},"question": "Two consecutive controls are both beyond –2s from the mean. How frequently would this occur on the basis of chance alone?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to assess validity/Accuracy of procedures/Quality control/2"},{"choices": ["Four consecutive controls are greater than ±1 standard deviation from the mean","Two controls in the same run are greater than 4s units apart","Two consecutive controls in the same run are each greater than ±4s from the mean","There is a shift above the mean for four consecutive controls"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Two controls in the same run are greater than 4s units apart","explanation": "The R4s rule is applied to two control levels within the same run. The rule is violated when the algebraic difference between them (level 1 – level 2) exceeds 4s. The rule is never applied across different runs. The R4s rule detects RE (error caused by lack of precision)"},"question": "The term R4S means that:","reference": "Chemistry/Evaluate laboratory data to assess validity/Accuracy of procedures/Quality control/2"},{"choices": ["Deterioration of the reagent","Miscalibration of the instrument","Improper dilution of standards","Electronic noise"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Deterioration of the reagent","explanation": "A trend occurs when six or more consecutive QC results either increase or decrease in the same direction; however, this is not cause for rejection until a multirule is broken. Trends are SEs (affecting accuracy) linked to an unstable reagent, calibrator, or instrument condition. For example, loss of volatile acid from a reagent causes a steady pH increase, preventing separation of analyte from protein. This results in lower QC results each day"},"question": "A trend in QC results is most likely caused by:","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to assess validity/Accuracy of procedures/Quality control/2"},{"choices": ["Recalibrate, and then repeat controls followed by selected patient samples if QC is acceptable","Repeat the controls before taking any corrective action","Change the reagent lot, and then recalibrate","Prepare fresh standards, and recalibrate"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Recalibrate, and then repeat controls followed by selected patient samples if QC is acceptable","explanation": "When the 22s rule is broken, this usually means that excessive SE is present and corrective action is required (repeating just the QC will not correct the problem). If recalibration yields acceptable QC results, both sets of QC results and the corrective action taken are documented in the QC log. If the magnitude of the error is large enough to be medically significant, then all patient samples since the last previously acceptable QC should be repeated. If in question, the magnitude of the error can be evaluated by repeating abnormal patient samples. If the average difference between results before and after recalibration is greater than 2s or error limit, then all samples should be repeated since the last acceptable QC"},"question": "In most circumstances, when two controls within a run are both greater than ±2s from the mean, what action should be taken first?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to take corrective action according to predetermined criteria/Quality control/3"},{"choices": ["Using last month’s QC data to determine current target limits","Exclusion of any QC results greater than ±2s from the mean","Using control results from all shifts on which the assay is performed","Using limits determined by reference laboratories using the same method"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Exclusion of any QC results greater than ±2s from the mean","explanation": "Data between ±2s and ±3s must be included in calculations of the next month’s acceptable range. Elimination of these values would continuously reduce the distribution of QC results, making “out of control” situations a frequent occurrence. Generally, QC results greater than 3s are not used to calculate next month’s mean"},"question": "When establishing a QC acceptable range, which of the following practices is inappropriate?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Apply principles of laboratory operations/Quality control/2"},{"choices": ["Calcium (Ca) 2.5 0.3","Potassium (K) 4.0 0.4","Sodium (Na) 140 4.0","Chloride (Cl) 100 2.5"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Calcium (Ca) 2.5 0.3","explanation": "Although calcium has the lowest s, it represents the assay with poorest precision. Relative precision between different analytes or different levels of the same analyte must be evaluated by the CV because standard deviation is dependent on sample concentrations. CV = (s × 100)/Mean. This normalizes standard deviation to a mean of 100. The CV for calcium in the example is 12.0%"},"question": "Which of the following assays has the poorest precision? Analyte Mean (mmol/L) Standard Deviation","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Coefficient of variation/3"},{"choices": ["3.0%", "4.6%", "7.6%", "33.0%"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "3.0%","explanation": "The coefficient of variation is calculated by dividing the standard deviation by the mean and multiplying by 100. CV is the most appropriate statistic to use when comparing the precision of samples that have different means. For example, when comparing the precision of the level 1 control to the level 2 control, the coefficient of variation normalizes the variance to be independent of the mean. The analysis is more precise for the control with the lower CV"},"question": "Given the following data, calculate the coefficient of variation for glucose: Analyte Mean Standard Deviation Glucose 76 mg/dL 2.3","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Calculate/Statistics/2"},{"choices": ["Levy-Jennings","Tonks-Youden","CUSUM","Linear regression"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Levy-Jennings","explanation": "The Levy-Jennings plot is a graph of all QC results with concentration plotted on the y-axis and run number on the x-axis. The mean is at the center of the y-axis, and concentrations corresponding to –2 and +2s (or other specified control limits) are highlighted. Results are evaluated for multirule violations across both levels and runs. Corrective action for shifts and trends can be taken before QC rules are broken"},"question": "Which of the following plots is best for detecting all types of QC errors?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize problems/Quality control/2"},{"choices": ["Levy-Jennings","Tonks-Youden","CUSUM","Linear regression"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Tonks-Youden","explanation": "The Tonks-Youden plot is used for interlaboratory comparison of monthly means. The method mean for level 1 is at the center of the y-axis and mean for level 2 at the center of the x-axis. Lines are drawn from the means of both levels across the graph, dividing it into four equal quadrants. If a laboratory’s monthly means both plot in the lower left or upper right quadrants, then SE exists in its method"},"question": "Which of the following plots is best for comparison of precision and accuracy among laboratories?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize problems/Quality control/2"},{"choices": ["Levy-Jennings","Tonks-Youden","CUSUM","Histogram"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "CUSUM","explanation": "CUSUM points are the algebraic sum of the difference between each QC result and the mean. The y-axis is the sum of differences and the x-axis is the run number. The center of the y-axis is 0. Because QC results follow a random distribution, the points should distribute about the zero line. Results are out of control when the slope exceeds 45 degrees or a decision limit (e.g., ±2.7s) is exceeded"},"question": "Which plot will give the earliest indication of a shift or trend?","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Evaluate laboratory data to recognize problems/Quality control/2"},{"choices": ["Long-term stability","The matrix is similar to the specimens being tested","The concentration of analytes reflects the clinical range","Analyte concentration must be independent of the method of assay"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Analyte concentration must be independent of the method of assay","explanation": "Quality control materials are stable, made of the same components as the specimen, cover the dynamic linear range of the assay, and can be used for multiple analytes. The target mean for QC samples is determined from replicate assays by the user’s method, not the “true” concentration of the analyte. Out-of-control results are linked to analytic performance rather than to the inherent accuracy of the method"},"question": "All of the following are requirements for a QC material except:","reference": "Laboratory Operations/Apply principles of basic laboratory procedures/Quality control/2"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Calculations, Quality Control, and Statistics"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}